Joseph Jeffries Wilson papers, Inclusive: 1915-1961, undated, Bulk: 1934-1961
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Joseph Jeffries Wilson papers
Inclusive: 1915-1961, undated, Bulk: 1934-1961
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
575
Wilson, Joseph Jeffries
1 document box
The Joseph Jeffries Wilson papers contain personal, family, and A.J. Moore High School materials generated by Professor J.J. Wilson in his 37 years of working as principle at the school.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Joseph Jeffries Wilson, or J.J. Wilson (1905-1989), was born on 1905 August 27 to parents Bertrust T. Wilson Sr. (1868-1934) and Harriet Jeffries Bailey Wilson (1868-1953) in Waco, Texas. Bertrust Wilson, who had received a master's degree in mathematics at age nineteen, had been a professor at Guadalupe College and Central Texas College before becoming principal at A.J. Moore High School in Waco.
J.J. Wilson's early education included attending A.J. Moore High School in Waco, obtaining a Bachelor of Arts degree from Bishop College in Marshall, Texas, and a Master of Arts degree from Kansas University. He received a doctoral degree in 1954 from Paul Quinn College. He also helped his brother with a family business, the Wilson Rug Laundry. Wilson also married Margaret H. Wilson (1908-2009). The couple had one daughter, Kathy Wilson Goss.
In 1934, Wilson's father passed away while still in charge of A.J. Moore High School, leading to J.J. Wilson becoming the next principal of A.J. Moore. For the next thirty-seven years, he led A.J. Moore High School to academic success, with many high school students finding that their schooling at A.J. Moore prepared them well for life and further academic pursuits.
In 1971, with the closing of A.J. Moore High School, Wilson became assistant superintendent for secondary schools in Waco. It is unknown how long he held this position.
Professor J.J. Wilson passed away on 1989 October 6 and is buried in Doris Miller Memorial Park in Waco, Texas. Margaret Wilson lived on until passing on 2009 October 5. She is also buried in Doris Miller Memorial Park.
Scope and Content
The Joseph Jeffries Wilson papers contain personal and family materials, plus materials relating to A.J. Moore High School. The personal series includes correspondence, mostly about financial matters. The family series also contains mostly financial documents, including bank statements, legal documents, and tax forms. The Moore High School series includes correspondence and school board minutes regarding equal pay for African American teachers, Wilson's yearly teaching contracts, and several letters regarding financial operations of the school.
Joseph Jeffries Wilson went by a variety of names throughout his life. Commonly referred to J.J. Wilson in correspondence, at some point in his academic career, he became known as Professor J.J. Wilson, though he never taught on the university level. His students at A.J. Moore seem to have referred to him as Professor J.J. Wilson. He is also occasionally referred to as Dr. J.J. Wilson, probably after he received a doctorate from Paul Quinn College.
Arrangement
The Joseph Jeffries Wilson papers were arranged in several folders and a binder prior to processing.
Currently, the Joseph Jeffries Wilson papers are arranged in three series: I. Personal, II. Family, III. A.J. Moore High School.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 575. Acquired 2019-10-10
Related Resources
Related references
Beard, Bettie V. "A.J. Moore High School alumni owe debt to visionary principal." Waco Tribune Herald, 2017 July 6. Accessed 2020 February 13.
Find A Grave, Inc. "Burtrust T Wilson, Sr." Memorial #73165817. Databases. Accessed 2020 February 13.
Find A Grave, Inc. "Dr Joseph J Wilson." Memorial #70652475. Databases. Accessed 2020 February 13.
Find A Grave, Inc. "Margaret H Wilson Wilson." Memorial #42908401. Databases. Accessed 2020 February 13.
Sawyer, Amanda. "A.J. Moore High School." Waco History. Accessed 2020 February 13.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Moore High School (Waco, Tex.)
Places
Waco (Tex.).
Subjects
African Americans -- Segregation -- Texas -- Waco.; Segregation in education -- Texas.
Genres
Correspondence.; Financial records.; Financial statements.; Minutes (Records)
- Personal Materials, 1930-1961, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains correspondence, financial, and legal documents to do with J.J. Wilson or his family. This series is in good condition.
  - Correspondence, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Legal Documents, 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Poll Tax Receipts, 1920-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anderson Riley Estate, 1933-1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bank Statements (1 of 2), 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bank Statements (2 of 2), 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - City of Waco Taxes, 1930-1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Travel, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Driver's License, 1944, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Waco Style Review admission card, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - War Ration book, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Family Materials, 1915-1961; 2
  This series contains resources related to Joseph Jeffries Wilson's extended family, especially financial matters related to his mother after his father had already passed away. This series is in average condition.
  - Correspondence, 1915-1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Legal, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Financial, 1940-1956 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Education, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bank Statements, 1944-1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - City of Waco Taxes, 1936-1958 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Medical, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- A.J. Moore High School, 1932-1952; 3
  This series contains information relating to A.J. Moore High School, where Professor J.J. Wilson served as principal for thirty-seven years. This series is in good condition.
  - Correspondence, 1932-1946 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - School Board Minutes, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Contracts, 1932-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Waco Independence School District receipts, 1936-1952 (Box 1, Folder 26)